Guide to the Democratic Socialists of America Records TAM.105
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Democratic Socialists of America Records
Bulk, 1972-1995
1940-2006
TAM.105
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
142.25 linear feet in 148 boxes
Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) was founded in 1973 as the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee and led by Michael Harrington (1928-1989), best known as the author of The Other America (1962) and became DSA upon its merger with the New American Movement (a New Left organization) in 1982. The collection contains administrative records, including convention materials, minutes, correspondence (including that of Michael Harrington), photographs, state and local chapter files, including local publications, membership files, committee, project, and topical files; correspondence and some administrative records of DSA's Youth Section; reports and proceedings of the Socialist International, of which DSA is the U.S. affiliate. The collection also contains published and unpublished writings of Michael Harrington and files relating to his travel and speaking engagements.
Democratic Socialists of America.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist.
Scope and Contents note
The collection contains administrative records, including convention materials; minute; photographs; correspondence (including that of Michael Harrington); state and local chapter files, including local publications, membership files, committee, project, and topical files; correspondence and some administrative records of the DSA's Youth Section; reports and proceedings of the Socialist International, of which DSA is the U.S. affiliate; files on the DSA-founded Institute for Democratic Socialism; and files on other labor and left organizations. The collection also contains published and unpublished writings of Michael Harrington and files relating to his travel and speaking engagements. In addition to Harringon, the principal correspondents are national leaders Carl Shier, Jack Clark, Maxine Phillips, and Frank Llewellyn. While we have noted isolated files of Michal Harrington correspondence (in addition to the several boxes consisting exclusively of his correspondence), there is some additional Harrington correspondence scattered thoughout the collection.
Historical/Biographical Note
Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) was founded in 1973 as the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) and led by Michael Harrington (1928-1989), best known as the author of The Other America (1962) and became the DSA upon its merger with the New American Movement (a New Left youth organization) in 1982. Harrington and others who left the Socialist Party-Social Democratic Foundation over its support of the Vietnam War were among the principal founders of DSOC. DSA established chapters in virtually every state, including chapters at many colleges and universities, worked to build a progressive presence in the Democratic Party through its Democratic Agenda project, worked closely with progressive labor unions and leaders, feminists and others to promote a social democratic agenda and a peaceful foreign policy, and advocated for socialism while strongly criticising Communism. DSA also published Democratic Left, founded the Socialist Scholars Conference (now known as the Left Forum), and established the Insitute for Democratic Socialism. DSA is the U.S. affiliate of the Socialist International.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Related Archival Materials
New American Movement Records (TAM 051)
Michael Harrington Papers (TAM 209)
Maurice Isserman Research Files for The Other American: The Life of Michael Harrington (TAM 239)
Accruals note
Additional accruals are expected.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Democratic Socialists of America. The collection was received in several accessions.
Clark, Jack, 1949-; Democratic left.; Democratic National Convention |d (1976: |c New York, N.Y.).; Democratic National Convention |d (1980: |c New York, N.Y.).; Democratic Party (U.S.).; Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (U.S.).; Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee. Youth Section.; Democratic Socialists of America. Democratic Agenda.; Democratic Socialists of America. Feminist Commission.; Democratic Socialists of America. Youth Section.; Harrington, Michael, 1928-1989; Institute for Democratic Socialism (U.S.).; New American Movement (Organization).; Newsletter of the Democratic Left.; Phillips, Maxine; Shier, Carl; Socialist International (1951- ).; Socialist Party-Social Democratic Federation.; Audiocassettes.; Circular letters.; College students |x Political activity |z United States.; Correspondence.; Labor unions and socialism |z United States.; Lectures.; Mailing lists.; Manuscripts (document genre); Manuscripts for publication.; Minutes.; New Left |z United States.; Newsletters.; Poverty |z United States.; Proceedings.; Reports.; Socialism and youth |z United States.; Socialism |z United States |v Periodicals.; Socialism |z United States |x History.; Socialism |z United States.; Speeches.; Surveys (documents).; Videocassettes.; Women and socialism |z United States.
- Records: Formation and early years; the majority of which is Michael Harrington correspondence., 1966-1973 (Box 1)
  Scope and Content Note
  FOLDER LIST:
  1 Michael Harrington, Correspondence 1971
  2 Michael Harrington, Correspondence 1971
  3 Michael Harrington, Correspondence 1972
  4 Michael Harrington, Correspondence 1973
  5 Michael Harrington, Correspondence 1973
  6 Carl Shier/Coalition Caucus 1966, 1967, 1971
  7 Carl Shier/Coalition Caucus 1972
  8 Carl Shier/Coalition Caucus 1973
  9 Michael Harrington, Writings unpublished 1970-1971
  10 Michael Harrington, Writings unpublished 1972
  11 Michael Harrington, Writings unpublished 1973
  13 Writings of Others 1971, 1973 14 Unidentified Writings 1972
  15 American Federation of Teachers 1973
  15a DSOC, Background and Formation clippings 1971-1973
  16 New York City Politics 1971
  16a Speaking Engagements 1971-1972
  17 United Auto Workers, Affirmative Action 1973
  18 Union Democracy Review 1973
  19 Memorabilia 1959-1973
- Records: DSOC Formation and early years, circa 11975-circa 1981 (Box 1A)
  1 N.D Remarks on DSOC
  2 1981 Discussion bulletins
  3 1973, 1976 7 Press releases
  4 1975(?) Convention diary
  5 May 1981 Pre Convention memos 6 May 1981 Resolutions, amendments
  7 May 1981 Reports, correspondence, agenda
  8 May 1981 Reports, correspondence, agenda
  9 May 1981 Convention memos, appointments
  10 May 1981 Workshops correspondence, topics
  11 May 1981 At large delegate correspondence
  National Board
  12 Jan 1980 Memos, proposed amendments, resolutions, report, rules, NAM/DSOC document
  13 June 1980 Minutes, resolutions, amendments, agenda, memos, reports, correspondence
  14 June 1980 Youth and Peace Work reports
  15 Jan 1981 Minutes, resolutions, amendments
  Youth Section
  16 1979-81 Minutes, reports, constitution, resolutions, amendments, agendas
  17 1979-81 Keylist memos, proposal, clippings
  18 1979-81 Correspondence, memos, institutions list, conference program, notices, pamphlet, songs
  19 1980 Summer mailing lists, correspondence
  20 1980 Summer Youth Conference correspondence, list of participants
  21 980-81 Days of Decision publications
  22 1981 IUSY trip applications, fundraising letters
  National Executive Committee (NEC)
  23 1980 Minutes, agenda, correspondence
  24 1981 Draft resolutions, reports, memos, correspondence, statement
  25 March 1981 Minutes, correspondence, reports
  26 Oct. 1981 Minutes, correspondence, reports, memos, notices, agendas, draft resolutions
  Commissions, Committees, Task Forces, Caucuses and Projects
  27 1980-81 Program committees: memos, correspondence, statements, form letters
  28 1980 Subcommittee meetings: agendas, statements, resolutions, amendments, recommendations
  29 1979-80 Democratic Agenda Conference: bulletin, reports
  30 1977 Education Task Force: memos, correspondence, readings lists
  31 1980 Health Care Task Force: newsletter and subscription form, bibliography
  32 1977-78 Hispanic Commission: reports, correspondence, memos, newsletters
  33 1977-78 Industrial Democracy Task Force: essay, bibliographies, correspondence
  34 1981 Jewish Commisssion: proposal
  35 March, 1978 Lawyer`s Caucus: letter
  36 1978-79 Committee on Religion and Socialism: newsletters, correspondence, activists list
  37 Aug, Oct 1981 Temporary Interim Committee: minutes
- Records: DSOC Formation and Early Years: Carl Shier Correspondence, 1971-1978 (Box 1B)
- Records: DSOC Formation and Early Years (Box 1C)
  Contents (folders):
  01. Election to DSOC Convention. 1975
  02. General Correspondence and Mailing List. ca. 1979
  03. Michael Harrington as Delegate to Interim Convention of Democratic Party. 1974
  04. Michael Harrington: Open Letter to DSOC. Jun 1973
  05. Key List. 1974-1975
  06. Representative Larry McDonald on DSOC. 1978
  07. Membership Reports. 1975-1976
  08. Midwest Labor Conference. 1973-74, 1976
  08A. Minority Recruitment. 1977
  09. National Alliance Against Racism. 1973-1977
  10. National Board. Oct 12, 1973
  11. National Board. Feb 14, 1974 - May 19, 1974
  12. National Board. Mar 1975
  13. National Board. Dec 13, 1975
  14. National Board. 1974-1976
  15. National Board. Mar 13, 1976
  16. National Board. 1977
  17. National Board. 1978
  18. National Board. 1979
  19. National Office Committee/National Steering Committee. 1973
  20. National Office Committee. 1974
  21. National Office Committee. 1975
  22. National Office Committee. 1976-1977
- Records: DSOC Formation and Early Years (Box 1D)
  01. National Office Committee. 1978
  02. Organizers Institute. Undated
  03. Olaf Palme Reception. Oct 17, 1975
  04. Puerto Rico. 1977-1978
  05. Public Events. 1975
  06. Portugal Mailgram Campaign. Jul 1975-Aug 1975
  07. Portugal Rights Defense Fund. 1976
  08. Socialist Filmstrip. 1975-1976
  09. Socialist Weekends. 1973-1975
  10. Soviet Jewry (Political Prisoners). 1977-1979
  11. Speakers Bureau. 1975
  12. Staff Meetings. 1976-1977
  13. Staff Meetings. 1978
  14. Staff Meetings. 1979
  15. Stencils, Form Letters. Undated
  16. J.P Stevens Campaign. 1975-1978
  17. Youth Conference Registrations. 1975
- Records: DSA: Early Years (processed portion), 1973-1982 (box 1 of 4), 1973-1981; this is probably one of the 3 boxes done by Alizah Zinsberg many years ago; the other two are presumably at CS in aisle 40D (Box 2)
  Subgroup I: DSOC
  Series 1: Organizational Overview
  Folder
  Series 2: Conventions
  7- 8 May 1981 Reports, correspondence, agenda
  Series 3: National Board
  Series 4: Youth Section
  21 1980-81 Days of Decision publications
  22 1981 IUSY (Int'l Union of Socialist Youth) trip applications, fundraising letters
  Series 5: National Executive Committee (NEC)
  25 Mar 1981 Minutes, correspondence, reports
  26 Oct 1981 Minutes, correspondence, reports, memos, notices, agendas, draft resolutions Series 6: Commissions, Committees, Task Forces, Caucuses and Projects
  35 Mar 1978 Lawyer`s Caucus: letter
- Records: DSA: Early Years (processed portion), 1973-1982 (box 2 of 4), 1976-1982 (Box 2A)
  Series 7: Locals, State and Regional Organizations
  1 1980-82 Alabama: correspondence, notices
  2 1980-81 Alaska: correspondence, notice, clippings
  3 1979-80 California: resolution, clippings
  4 1978-81 California, Bay Area: form letters, correspondence, proposal, report, calendars, notices
  5 1980-82 California, Los Angeles: minutes,report, correspondence
  6 1978-80 California, Sacremento Valley: correspondence, notices, clippings, song
  7 1979-81 California, San Diego: minutes, correspondence, notices, clippings, agendas
  8 1981-82 California, Santa Cruz: report, publication, clipping
  9 1979-80 Colorado: correspondence, bulletin
  10 1980-82 Connecticut: correspondence, notices, clippings
  11 1979-82 D.C., Washington: correspondence, memos, report, clippings
  12 1980-81 Florida: correspondence
  13 1979-81 Georgia: correspondence
  14 1980 Georgia, Atlanta: constitution, letter
  15 1980-81 Illinois: correspondence
  16 1978-81 Illinois, Chicago: correspondence, report, clippings
  17 1980 Illinois, Champaign Urbana: correspondence, notices
  18 1980 Illinois, Springfield: correspondence
  19 1980-81 Indiana: correspondence
  20 1979-81 Iowa: correspondence, notices
  21 1980 Kansas: correspondence
  22 1980-82 Kentucky: correspondence, clippings
  23 1980 Louisiana: correspondence
  24 1980, 1982 Maine: correspondence
  25 1980 Maryland: correspondence
  26 1980-81 Massachusetts: correspondence, invitation
  27 1980-82 Mass., Boston: correspondence, clippings, notice, pamphlet
  28 1979-82 Michigan: correspondence, notices, pamphlets
  29 1980-82 Minnesota: correspondence, memos, clipping
  30 1980 Mississippi: correspondence
  31 1980-82 Missouri: correspondence, notices
  32 1980 New Hampshire: correspondence
  33 1980-81 New Jersey: correspondence, notice
  34 1980 New Mexico: correspondence
  35 1981-82 New York Albany, Ithaca: annual report, correspondence, notice
  36 1980, 1982 New York, Nassau County: correspondence, notices, statement of principles, clippings
  37 1978-81 New York, New York City: correspondence, memos, statements, notices, pamphlets
  38 1980-81 New York, Rochester: annual report, correspondence, notices, invoices
  39 1980-81 New York, Suffolk County: correspondence, clipping, notices
  40 1979-82 North Carolina: correspondence, notice
  41 1980-81 Ohio: correspondence, memos
  42 1980-82 Oregon: annual report, correspondence, resolution, memos, clippings, poster ad
  43 1979-81 Pennsylvania: correspondence, memos, notices, brochures
  44 1979-82 Rhode Island: annual report, correspondence, notices
  45 1979-82 Tennessee: correspondence, memos, schedule
  46 1979-82 Texas: correspondence, membership roster, report, notices, clipping
  47 1980-81 Vermont: minutes, correspondence, notices, clippings
  48 1979-80 Virginia: correspondence, constitution, bylaws; 1982--report, notices
  49 1979-82 Washington state: annual report, preamble, correspondence, memos, notices, clippings
  50 1980-81 Wisconsin: correspondence, notices, news release, clipping newsletters:
  51 Oct 1977-Jun 1978 Grass Roots (newsletter of the locals)
  52 1976-77, 1979 California: Bay Area
  53 1978-81 California, Los Angeles
  54 1980 Colorado
  55 1979-82 Illinois, Champaign-Urbana
- Records: DSA: Early Years (processed portion), 1973-1982 (box 3 of 4), 1976-1982 (Box 2B)
  1 1977-82 D.C., Washington
  2 1976-80 Illinois, Chicago
  3 1976, 1979-80 Maine 4 1978, 1982 Maryland
  5 1976-77 Massachussets
  6 1978-82 Michigan
  7 1978-81 Minnesota
  8 1979-81 Missouri
  9 1979 New England
  10 1979 New Jersey
  11 1981-82 New York Albany, Ithaca, Rochester
  12 1977-79 New York Nassau County
  13 1978 New York Suffolk County
  14 1977-78 Oregon
  15 1978-81 Pennsylvania, Philadelphia
  16 1978 Pennsylvania, Pittsburgh
  17 1981-82 Virginia
  18 1977-78; 1981-82 Wisconsin
  Series 8: Administrative Files
  19 1978-80 Staff meetings minutes, memos
  20 1981 Keylist memos
  21 1981 Debs Thomas dinner form letters
  22 1981 Willy Brandt reception: invitation, responses
- Records: DSA: Early Years (processed portion), 1973-1982 (box 3 of 4) (Box 2C)
  23 1978-79 General form letters, dues reminders, registration form
  24 1980 Personnel and Management Committee memo / application for National Director
  25 Nov 8-14, 1980 Time diary
  26 1980-81 Travel schedules
  27 1980-81 Fundraising activities, correspondence
  Series 9: Newsclippings and Misc.
  28 1977-81 Newsclippings, letter, calendar
  Subgroup II: DSOC/NAM
  Series 1: Conventions
  29 Aug 1979 Convention agenda
  30 July 1980 NAM Convention resolutions, amendments, general information, factsheet, report, chapter membership data, candidacy statements, form letter, songsheet
  Series 2: Joint Publications
  31 1980-81 Letter, questionaire, bulletin, pamphlet, memo
- Records: Michael Harrington Correspondence, 1971-May 1979 (Box 3)
- Records: Michael Harrington Correspondence, Jun 1979-May 1982 (Box 4)
- Records: Michael Harrington Correspondence, Jun 1982-Jan 1987; General Correspondence, Jul 1979-Jun 1979, 1975-1987 (Box 5)
- Records: General Correspondence, Jul 1979-Jan 1983; "General Correspondence" with State and Local Chapters, 1972-1973 (Enumerated in note below), 1972-Jan 1983 (Box 6)
  General Correspondence: Long Island, 1973-1974
  General Correspondence: Minnesota, 1974-1975
  General Correspondence: Mississippi, 1974
  General Correspondence: Montana, 1974
  General Correspondence: New Hampshire, 1972-1975
  General Correspondence: New Jersey, 1974-1975
  General Correspondence: New Mexico, 1973-1974
  General Correspondence: New York City, 1973-1976 (two folders)
  Meeting Notes: New York City, 1973-1975
  General Correspondence: New York Local DSOC Steering Committee Minutes, 1973
  General Correspondence: New York State, 1971-1975 (four folders)
  General Correspondence: North Carolina, 1973-1975
  General Correspondence: Ohio, 1973-1975 (three folders)
  General Correspondence: Oklahoma, 1973-1974
  General Correspondence: Tennessee, 1975
- Records: About half the box contains Youth Section correspondence, 1976-1982; there are files from the 1979 convention in Houston; four thick files labeled "non-correspondence" contain national office administrative records, including circular letters, minutes and reports, and a few untitled typescripts, possibly by Harrington, and miscellaneous files, including "Tom Kahn and S.D. Criticism of DSOC Nuclear Policy," and "Dechartering of Miami Local (Box 7)
- Records: Michael Harrington Writings and Travel / Speaking Engagements Correspondence; Miscellaneous Administrative Records and Subject Files. Includes Harrington typescripts: "Two Cheers for the 80s" and "Defining and Defending the Public Interest" and a few untitled Harrington typescripts, 1976-1981 (Box 8)
- Records: Includes Minutes (national-level), 1979 Convention (Houston), five thick files "Biographical Information on Members"; two thick files from the 1981 Search Committee (for a National Director); files on various committee, projects and topics, including one thick file on Democratic Agenda (DSA's initiative within the Democratic Party), 1974-1982 (Box 9)
- Records: About half the box contains folders labeled "non-correspondence" which contain administrative records, mostly from 1980-1981 (circulars, corespondence, reports, contact lists, printed ephemera, some concerned with the allied Institute for Democratic Socialism); there is also one small folder of Harrington correspondence (1981), and two folders, titled, respectively, "Harrington-Robert Bleiberg Debate (1977), and "Harrington, DSOC and the Social Democrats", 1970s-1980s (Box 10)
- Records: General Correspondence (National Office), May 1978-Jan 1988 (Box 11)
- Records: Youth Section Correspondence, Feb 1977-Jan 1988 (Box 11A)
- Records: People's Power Project (Public, other energy program), 1975-76; Chapter files, mostly laphabetical by City, including publications, 1977-79; one thick file of New American Movement reports, 1977-78., 1975-1979 (Box 12)
- Records: Democratic Agenda, 1976-80, 1976-1980 (Box 12A)
- Records: Democratic Agenda, 1975-76, 1975-1976 (Box 12B)
- Records: Key List Mailings, 1973-78; National Office Committee Minutes, 1979; Natioal Board Minutes, May 1979; DSOC direrctory and questionnaires, 1978-79 (one file)., 1973-1979 (Box 12C1)
- Records: Conventions: 1975, 1977; National Executive Committee, 1979; Institute for Socialist Organizers, June 1975; Conference, Jan 1976. (Box 12C2)
- Records: National Board, 1973-80, including 1973 elections; Feminist Commission, 1978-79; Internal Discussion (1 thick file, 1976); Ad[vertising] Council, 1973-1980 (Box 12D)
- Records: Convention, 1981, including discussion of merger with NAM; bulk of box pertains to Democratic Party, its 1980 convention, and Edward Kennedy's campaign for the presidential nomination, 1980-1981 (Box 12E)
- Records: bulk of box pertains to Democratic Agenda, 1977-78, and related topical files'; several files of genral correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 12F)
- Records: Democratic Agenda - Democratic Party, 1976, 1976-1976 (Box 12G)
- Records: DSOC Local and Regional Files - Alabama -- New York, 1975-1979 (Box 13)
- Records: Other Organizations and Publications Files (labor and left), Topical Files, mostly beginning with the letters I---T, several like files beginning with the letter A., 1975-1979 (Box 13A)
- Records: About one-third of the box consists of untitled folders of National Office materials, including circulars, correspondence, position papers and reports, much concerned with activity within the Democratic Party, including Democratic Agenda; the remainder of the box consists of files on organizations arranged alphabetically, American--Committee, including a thick file on Breira: A Project of Concern in Diaspora-Israeli Relations., 1975-1980 (Box 13B)
- Records: The first third of the box consists of files on organizations, arranged alphabetically, Congress--Indians; several miscellaneous files relating to New York City area issues; with the last half of the box containing files on college and university chapters, the majority in New York State, but also including schools in Texas through Virginia and several other schools., 1974-1989 (Box 14)
- Records: Includes several thick files from the formative years, 1972-93, including material from Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, Social Democrats, USA (and response to Harrington's resignation therefrom); several thick files of early DSOC administrative records, 1974--, with some writings, possibly by Harrington; DSOC State level organization files for states beginning with "A"; a file containing contact information for key people for chapters around the country; and several organizational and topical files, the latter chiefly relating to economic issues, such as full employment, 1972-1978 (Box 15)
- Records: Includes a file on the State of California, and files on states Oklahoma--Wyoming; these files chiefly contain correspondence with / from the national office, and the most frequent correspondent is Jack Clark, with some correspondence of Harrington also present. Note that this box is only 0.5 linear ft., ca. 1974-ca. 1979 (Box 15A)
- Records: Includes State and Chapter files, including local newsletters, Pennsylvania--Tennessee; several California chapters' files; two files of minutes: one from the Dec, 1987 Executive Committee, the other from the May 1988 National Executive Committee; miscellaneous national administrative files, and two files from the Youth Section, 1983-1988 (Box 16)
- Records: Chiefly contains files of various NY State Chapters, including publications, from the 1980s; one thick file of national administrative materials ca. 1984; several files on the Local Development Func, 1991-1993, 1980-1993 (Box 17)
- Records: Includes one thick file of Carl Shier correspondence, 1972-74; State chapters' files from the majority of letters in the alphabet, 1973-75; one file from the founding period of 1972-73 contining materials from DSOC's predecessor organizations; a file of undated ballots for National Board membership; and several Local Development project files, 1991-92., Bulk, 1972-1975; 1972-1992 (Box 17A)
- Records: The bulk of the box consists of State chapters' files from Iowa--Montana, including local publications, 1984-1988; a file on an October, 1981 meeting on national priorities; and several files on the Local Development project, early 1990s., 1981-1991 (Box 18)